<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Drie artiickelen aengaende een moderatie te hebben in de proceduyren van de inquisitie tegens de Con. Maijesteyt van Engelants onderdanen, in Spanien op dat elck onderrecht mach ziin van den inhouden van dese secrete artijckelen, siet hier een extract van dien in Engels, ende t'selve van woorde te woorde overghestelt in Duytsch, ghetrocken uyt de copije ghedruckt by Robert Barker printer van de Con. Meest Excell. Maijesteyt, anno 1606.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1609</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 18 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A22703</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 9211.2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S812</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22741955</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22741955</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25695</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A22703)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25695)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1775:42)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Drie artiickelen aengaende een moderatie te hebben in de proceduyren van de inquisitie tegens de Con. Maijesteyt van Engelants onderdanen, in Spanien op dat elck onderrecht mach ziin van den inhouden van dese secrete artijckelen, siet hier een extract van dien in Engels, ende t'selve van woorde te woorde overghestelt in Duytsch, ghetrocken uyt de copije ghedruckt by Robert Barker printer van de Con. Meest Excell. Maijesteyt, anno 1606.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas Basson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Tot Leyden :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1609.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An extract, in Dutch and English, of "Articles of peace, entercourse, and commerce, concluded in the names of James and Philip the third, and Albertus and Isabella" which discusses a moderation in the proceedings of the Inquisition.--Cf. STC (2nd ed.).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="dut">dut</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Foreign relations --  Spain --  1603-1625.</term>
               <term>Spain --  Foreign relations --  Great Britain --  1516-1700.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <!-- Text was keyed along with the unrelated VID 25692 / STC 9200.3 -->
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25695:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25695:1"/>
            <p>Drie <hi>ARTIICKELEN</hi> aengaende <hi>Een Moderatie te hebben in de proceduyren van de Inquiſitie tegens de Con. Maijeſteyt van En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelants onderdanen; in Spanien</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Op dat elck onderrecht mach zijn van den inhouden van deſe ſecrete Artijckelen / ſiet hier een extract van dien in Engels / ende t'ſelve van woorde te woorde overgheſtelt in duytſch / ghetrocken uyt de copije ghedruckt by Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Barker Printer van de Con. meeſt excell. Maije<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteyt. anno <hi>1606.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>TOT LEYDEN,</hi> By Thomas Baſſon / <hi>1609.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div xml:lang="eng" type="article">
            <pb facs="tcp:25695:2"/>
            <head>Three articles concerning a moderation to be had in the proceedings of the Inquiſition, toward the Kings Maieſties ſubiects, in Spaine.</head>
            <div n="1" type="article">
               <p>FIrſt, if they haue exceeded in any thing before theyr entran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce into Spaine, they ſhall not be called into the Inquiſition for the ſame, neither ſhall bee moleſted for any of thoſe things ſo committed, out of Spaine, neither ſhall any account for the ſame bee demaunded of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="article">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>Alſoo if they will not enter into the Churches, no man ſhall compell them thereunto, but if they doe enter into the ſame, they ſhall performe thoſe dueties and revere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, which are uſed towards the holy Sacrament of the Altaer being there, and if they ſhall ſee the holy Sacrament comming towards them in any ſtreete they ſhall doe reverence by bowing their knees, or elſe to paſſe aſide by ſome other ſtreete, or turne into ſome houſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="article">
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>And if any of the ſaide perſons being Maſters or Maſter ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, or any other Officers of ſhips, wich bee not their owne, doe exceed in any matter herein, the Inquiſition proceeding againſt them by Office, is onely to ſequeſter their owne proper goods, and are to leave free the ſhips and all other goods, not belonging to the offenders; the ſame is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood for the Traders and Factors.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="dut" type="article">
            <pb facs="tcp:25695:2"/>
            <head>Drie artijckelen aengaende een moderatie te hebben in de proceduyren van de Inquiſitie teghens de Co. Ma. onderdanen in Spanien.</head>
            <div n="1" type="article">
               <p>EErſt / of zyluyden hebben gheexcedeert in eenich dinck voor haerluyder innecomen in Spanien / zyluyden en ſullen niet zijn gheropen in de Inquiſitie voor de ſelve / nochte ſullen zijn gemoleſteert voor eenich van deſe dingen ſo bedreven / buyten Spanien / nochte en ſal eenige reecken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſchap voor de ſelve zijn afgheeyſcht van hem.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="article">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>Ooc of zyluyden willen niet gaen in de kercken / niemant ſal dwingen haer daer toe / maer of zyluyden gaen in de ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve / zyluyden ſullen voldoen deſe plichten ende reverencien / de welcke werden ghebruyckt tegens het heylighe Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment des Altaers weſende daer: ende of zyluyden ſullen ſien het heylighe Sacrament comende ieghens hem in eenighe ſtrate / ſy ſullen doen reverencie mit buyginghe heurluyder knien / of anders te treden ter zijden in eenige ander ſtraet / of keeren in eenich huys.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="article">
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>Ende of eenighe vande voornoemde perſonen / weſende Meeſters of Meeſterſ-maets / of eenich ander Officiers van ſchepen / de welcke zijn niet haer eyghen / te buyten ginghen eenigher manieren hier inne / de Inquiſitie procederende te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gens hem Amptſhalven heeſt alleenlijcken te ſequeſtreren haer luyden eygen ſelfs goeden / ende hebben te laten vrij de ſcheepen ende alle andere goeden niet belanghende aen de miſdoenders: Tſelve is oock te verſtaen vande Reeders en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de Factoors.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
